Mackenzie Urquhart-Cronish

September 2018 - Present

Supervisor: Amy Angert

September 2009 - June 2013

Ph.D. Candidate
Botany Dept. & Biodiversity Research Centre
University of British Columbia
murquhart@biodiversity.ubc.ca
macurqcron.github.io

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My PhD research focuses on understanding the demographic pathways and genetic consequences of range expansion in plants. I am interested in expanding on current evolutionary theory that predicts negative fitness consequences on the range edge (e.g., mutation accumulation, decreased genetic variation) as a result of range expansion by developing new theoretical models and conducting empirical investigations in nature along contrasting spatiotemporal scales (e.g., latitudinal and elevational gradients). Specifically, I want to identify when and where we would expect spread to impact spatial patterns in plant mating-system type and the long-term persistence of edge plant populations in nature, which has implications for population-level responses to climate change.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. Candidate

University of British Columbia Department of Botany

M.Sc.

September 2014 - July 2016
University of Toronto
Supervisor: Marla Sokolowski

Department of Ecology & Evolutionary Biology

B.Sc. Hon. with distinction

University of Toronto Supervisor: Marla Sokolowski

Double major: Ecology & Evolutionary Biology and Animal Physiology

PUBLICATIONS

Peer-reviewed

- 4. R. Germain, M. Urquhart-Cronish, N. Jones, M. Mayfield, and M. Raymundo (*In press*). The strength and direction of (mal)adaptation depends on neighbour density and the environment. *Journal of Ecology*.
- 3. K.A. Thompson, M. Urquhart-Cronish, K.D. Whitney, L.H. Rieseberg, and D. Schluter (2021). Patterns, predictors, and consequences of dominance in hybrids. *The American Naturalist.* 197(3), E72-E88 (*Honorable mention: Best student paper award 2022*)
- 2. M. Urquhart-Cronish, and S. P. Otto (2019). Gender and language use in scientific grant writing. *FACETS*. 4: 442-458.

press: University Affairs article

1. **M.** Urquhart-Cronish and M. B. Sokolowski (2014). Gene-environment interplay in *Drosophila melanogaster*: chronic nutritional deprivation in larval life affects adult fecal output. *Journal of Insect Physiology.* 69: 95-100.

AWARDS

Scholarships & fellowships

| 2022 | Kit Malkin Scholarship | \$775 CAD |
|-------------|---|--------------------------|
| 2020 – 2021 | NSERC CGS D | $$35\ 000\ \mathrm{CAD}$ |
| 2020 | L'Oréal - France-Canada Research Fund Fellowship | $$5~000~\mathrm{CAD}$ |
| 2019 | Vladimir J. Krajina Prize in Plant Ecology | \$1 200 CAD |
| 2019 | Samantha Hicks Memorial Prize | 1050 CAD |
| 2018 – 2020 | NSERC PGS D | \$42 000 CAD |
| 2018-2022 | UBC Four-Year Fellowship $(\frac{3}{4} \text{ declined})$ | \$72 800 CAD |
| 2015 & 2016 | Frederick P. Ide Graduate Award | 2020 CAD |
| 2015 – 2016 | NSERC CGS M | \$17 500 CAD |
| 2014 | EEB Entrance Scholarship | \$1 000 CAD |
| 2012 | Victoria College In-Course Regents Scholarship | \$1 000 CAD |

Research grants

| 2022 | The American Society of Naturalists Student Research Award | \$2 000 USD |
|------|--|-----------------------|
| 2021 | Lewis and Clark Fund for Exploration and Field Research | $$5~000~\mathrm{USD}$ |
| 2020 | RC Lewontin Award. Society for the Study of Evolution | \$2 500 USD |

Travel awards

| 2016 | School of Graduate Studies Conference Grant | \$500 CAD |
|------|---|-----------|
| 2016 | Harold H. Harvey Travel Award | \$400 CAD |
| 2014 | Imperial College Travel Grant | £500 UK |

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Mentorship

2019–2020 Olivia Rahn UBC 'SURE' Award, Directed Studies, & NSERC USRA (UBC)

Courses taught

| 2022 | Teaching assistant | Integrative Science Research Development Project (UBC) |
|------------------|--------------------|--|
| 2020, 2021, 2022 | Teaching assistant | Plant Ecology (UBC) |
| 2021 | Teaching assistant | Fundamentals of Biostatistics (UBC) |
| 2020 | Teaching assistant | Plants and People (UBC) |
| 2015, 2016 | Teaching assistant | From Genomes to Ecosystems (U of T) |
| 2014 | Teaching assistant | Adaptation and Biodiversity (U of T) |

CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

| ‡Ta | lk [†] Poster *Presentation award | | |
|------|---|-------------------------|--|
| 2022 | Botany Graduate Student Symposium [‡] | Vancouver, BC, Canada | |
| 2021 | Ecology & Evolution Virtual Retreat [‡] | Online | |
| 2019 | Ecology & Evolution retreat [†] | Brackendale, BC, Canada | |
| 2018 | Ecology & Evolution Retreat [†] | Brackendale, BC, Canada | |
| 2016 | Canadian Society for Ecology & Evolution [‡] | St. John's, NL, Canada | |
| 2016 | Ontario Ecology, Ethology & Evolution Colloquium [‡] | Toronto, ON, Canada | |
| 2013 | Ontario Ecology, Ethology & Evolution Colloquium [†] | London, ON, Canada | |
| 2013 | U of T EEB Department Undergraduate Poster Fair †* | Toronto, ON, Canada | |
| | | | |

PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

Technical experience

| 2018 | Field Crew Leader with Dr. Amy Angert | Vancouver, BC, Canada |
|-----------|---|-----------------------|
| 2018 | CIEE Website Developer with Dr. Diane Srivastava | Vancouver, BC, Canada |
| 2017 | Field and Greenhouse Technician with Dr. Rachel Germain | Vancouver, BC, Canada |
| 2017 | Grant Writer/Research Assistant with Dr. Sarah P. Otto | Vancouver, BC, Canada |
| 2016-2017 | Data Analyst with Dr. Jeannette Whitton | Vancouver, BC, Canada |
| 2013-2014 | Research Assistant with Dr. Marla B. Sokolowski | Toronto, ON, Canada |

COMMUNITY INVOLVEMENT & SERVICE

Positions held

| 9091 | UDC Condenda December 1 | C 1: C:-t f E1 0- E1t: |
|-------------|--|--|
| 2021- | UBC Graduate Representative | Canadian Society for Ecology & Evolution |
| 2018- | Webmaster | Angert Lab (UBC) |
| 2020 – 2021 | President | UBC Botany Graduate Students' Association |
| 2020 – 2021 | Ofice Space Use Committee | UBC Biodiversity Research Centre |
| 2019 | Co-director "Huts" Skit | UBC Botany & Zoology Departments |
| 2019 – 2020 | Wilderness First Aid Coordinator | UBC Botany & Zoology Departments |
| 2017 – 2018 | "Coexisting with Coyotes" Data Analyst | Stanley Park Ecology Society |
| 2016 – 2017 | Museum Outreach Education Volunteer | Beaty Biodiversity Museum |
| 2016 | Volunteer Tutor | U of T Saturday Program |
| 2015 - 2016 | Lead Plenary Coordinator | Ontario Ecology, Ethology & Evolution Colloquium |

Reviewer history

 $A cademic\ journals$

2021 Journal of Biogeography, Proc. Royal Soc. B.

2020 FACETS